Guide to the Paul L. Holmer Papers
Yale University Divinity School Library
Paul L. Holmer Papers
1876-2004
RG 195
Yale University Divinity School Library
16
39 boxes
Published and unpublished writings, notes, course-related material, and correspondence of Paul L. Holmer provide insight into his work and thought. Holmer (1916-2004) was Professor of Philosophical Theology at Yale from 1960 to 1987.
Holmer, Paul L., 1916-2004
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of the Holmer family.
Conditions Governing Access
Open to qualified researchers.
Biographical / Historical
1916 Nov 14 Born in Minneapolis, MN, son of Paul E. and Elsie (Johnson) Holmer
1940 B.A., University of Minnesota
1942 M.A., University of Minnesota
1944 Married Phyllis J. Schulberg --- children: Paul, Linnea, Jonathan
1944-1946 Instructor of philosophy at Yale
1946 Ph.D., Yale
1946 Taught at Gustavus Adolphus College
1946-1960 Professor of philosophy at University of Minnesota
1960-1987 Noah Porter Professor of Philosophical Theology, Yale Divinity School
1964-1965 Guggenheim Fellow
1987-2004 Noah Porter Emeritus Professor
2004 Jun 29 Died in St. Paul, MN
Scope and Contents
The Writings of Holmer in Series I are divided into seven sub-sections: his writings as a student, material related to published and unpublished book-length works, forewords to books, chapters in books, published articles, sermons, and lectures, unpublished essays and lectures, and reviews written by Holmer. In each sub-section dated writings are arranged chronologically, followed by undated works that are arranged alphabetically by title. Holmer published more than 100 articles, many of which are represented here. While an effort has been made to associate unpublished typescript writings with later published versions, there are undoubtedly cases where an association has not been drawn.
The Notes by Holmer contained in Series II are arranged alphabetically by topic or folder title. Most of the notes are undated handwritten sheets, which were received in an unorganized state. Some of the folders of notes contained a range of seemingly unrelated pages, but these "miscellaneous" groupings have been retained intact. Some of the notes are from the era when Holmer was a student while others appear to be notes for lectures, on reading, or preparatory for future writings. Notes for course lectures are primarily in Series III, Course-related Material, but it is likely that some of the notes in Series II were also course-related.
The Course-related Materials in Series III are arranged alphabetically by topic or course title. As noted above, there is overlap between Series II and Series III as it was not always easy to tell whether notes related to courses, lectures, or writings.
Series IV, Correspondence, is arranged chronlogically, dating from 1954 to 1996, with correspondents noted. The correspondence is primarily with Holmer's colleagues, students, publishers, or related to requests for Holmer to speak in various venues.
Series V, Personal Items and Memorabilia, includes biographical information about Holmer, including items from his student days, documentation of speaking engagements and other events attended, articles and interviews, and an obituary.
Series VI, Collected Material, consists primarily of writings by others. Reviews of works by Holmer are not in this series, but rather have been filed in Series I with the relevant work by Holmer. The last several folders in the collection are a very eclectic mixture of materials, which have been retained in the order received; the range of Holmer's interests and his methods of gathering material are reflected in these files.
Arrangement
I. Writings
II. Notes
III. Course-related Material
IV. Correspondence
V. Personal Items and Memorabilia
VI. Collected Material
Theology; Educators; Holmer, Paul L., 1916-2004
- Writings of Holmer, Series I
  - Writings as student
    - "The Psychology of Religion as seen in St. Benedict and Benedictine Monachism." (1 manuscript), 1940 Mar (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - "The Socialism of Pope Leo XIII as Seen by Selma Lagerlof." (1 manuscript, 1 letter from Robert Pearson), 1940 Jun (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - "Critical Review of Harry V.E. Palmblad's Strindberg's Conception of History ." (1 manuscript), 1940 Dec (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - "The Elan Vital and Will to Power Compared and Contrasted." (1 manuscript), 1941 Mar (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - "A Comparative Study of the Philosophies of Soren Kierkegaard and Friedrich Nietzsche: A Thesis Submitted to the Graduate Faculty of the University of Minnesota." (M.A. thesis; 1 manuscript), 1941 Dec (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - "The Problem of Epistemology in Saint Thomas." (1 manuscript), 1942 Dec (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - "Review of G.H. Joyce's Principles of Natural Theology ." (1 manuscript), 1943 Jan (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - "Kierkegaard and the Truth: An Analysis of the Presuppositions Integral to His Definition of the Truth." Dissertation, Yale (paperbound), 1945 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - "Kierkegaard and the Truth: An Analysis of the Presuppositions Integral to His Definition of the Truth." Dissertation, Yale (hardbound), 1945 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - "The Ethical Philosophy of Baruch Spinoza." (1 typescript, notes on Descartes, letter to "Carola"), ca.1936-1945 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - "History 51-5." American History notebook. (1 notebook), ca.1936-1945 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - "Oil: Uses, Products, Sources -- Am. Hist. 52-4th." (1 notebook), ca.1936-1945 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - "Outline: Robert Woodworth's 'Contemporary Schools of Psychology'." (1 manuscript), ca.1936-1945. (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - "Review of A.E. Taylor's Faith of a Moralist ." (1 typescript), ca.1936-1945 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - "St. Thomas' Theory of Value." (1 typescript), ca.1936-1945 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - "Theories of Abstraction in Lockian and Aristotelian Philosophy." (1 manuscript), ca.1936-1945 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - "The Value of History According to Barth and Brunner." (n.d.) (1 manuscript), ca.1936-1945 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Re. Book-length Works
    - Published works
      - re. Philosophy and the Common Life: (1960 Tully Cleon Knoles Lectures in Philosophy, College of the Pacific Philosophy Institute Publications Volume X, William D. Niemann, ed.): Typescripts: Ch. II - "Morality and the Inner Life"; Ch. III - "Morality and Some Intellectual Considerations" (Box 2, Folder 19)
      - re. Philosophy and the Common Life: Typescripts: Ch. II - "Morality and the Inner Life"; Ch. III - "Morality and Some Intellectual Considerations"; Ch. IV - "Morality and Religion", 1960 (Box 2, Folder 20)
      - re. Philosophy and the Common Life: Typescripts: Ch. IV - "Morality and Religion";photocopy of final published version, 1960 (Box 2, Folder 21)
      - re. Theology and the Scientific Study of Religion. (The Lutheran Studies Series: 2, Minneapolis: T.S. Denison and Co., 1961) - Ch. I - "Learning About the Christian Faith"; Untitled partial manuscripts (Box 2, Folder 22)
      - re. Theology and the Scientific Study of Religion - Typescript: Preface, 1961 (Box 2, Folder 23)
      - re. Theology and the Scientific Study of Religion - Typescripts: Preface; Table of Contents; Ch. I - "Theology, Church Life and Faith"; Ch. III - "Historical Research and Faith: Edmund Wilson"; Ch. IV :Historical Research and Christianity: Herbert Butterfield"; Ch. VI - "Society and Faith: Will Herberg", 1961 (Box 2, Folder 24)
      - re. Theology and the Scientific Study of Religion - Typescript: Ch. VII - "Faith and Faith: Martin Buber"; Notes on Buber; Flyer advertising Holmer's speaking engagement on Buber, 3/23/1978; Martin Buber Bibliographies, 1961 (Box 2, Folder 25)
      - re. Theology and the Scientific Study of Religion - Typescripts: Ch. VII - "Faith and Faith: Martin Buber"; Ch. VIII - "Culture and Faith: Romano Guardini"; Ch. IX - "Catholicism and Protestant Faith: Karl Adam"; Ch. X - "Ontology and Faith: Paul Tillich"; Ch. XI - "The Bible and Faith: H. H. Rowley", 1961 (Box 2, Folder 26)
      - re. Theology and the Scientific Study of Religion: Typescript: Ch. XI - "The Bible and Theology: H. H. Rowley", 1961 (Box 2, Folder 27)
      - re. Theology and the Scientific Study of Religion: Typescript: Ch. XII - "Language and Faith", 1961 (Box 2, Folder 28)
      - re. Theology and the Scientific Study of Religion - Typescripts: Ch. XII - "Language and Faith: Some Philosophers"; Ch. XIII - "Mythology and Faith: Rudolf Bultmann"; Ch. XV - "Philosophy and Faith: Albert Schweitzer"; Ch. XVI - "Everyman and Faith", 1961 (Box 2, Folder 29)
      - re. Theology and the Scientific Study of Religion - Typescript: Ch. XIII - "Mythology and Faith: Rudolf Bultmann", 1961 (Box 2, Folder 30)
      - re. Theology and the Scientific Study of Religion. Review by Harry N. Huxhold in Religion on Campus (Winter 1963) (Box 2, Folder 31)
      - re. Youth Considers Doubt and Frustration. (Youth Forum Series, Camden, NJ: Thomas Nelson and Sons, 1967) - Manuscript and editorial changes, comments (Box 3, Folder 32)
      - re. Youth Considers Doubt and Frustration: Typescripts: Ch. I - "On Doubting"; Ch. II - "Doubt and Knowledge"; Ch. III - "Doubt and Religion"; Ch. IV - "Science and Theology"; Ch. V - "Theological Beliefs"; Ch. VI - "Knowledge and Religion", 1967 (Box 3, Folder 33)
      - re. C. S. Lewis: The Shape of His Faith and Thought. New York: Harper and Row, 1976. (Complete typescript) (Box 3, Folder 34)
      - re. C.S. Lewis: The Shape of His Faith and Thought (New York: Harper and Row, 1976. / London: Sheldon Press, 1977, 1976.), incl. review by Mary McDermott Shideler in New Review of Books and Religion (Nov. 1976); review by Michael Zeik in Commonweal (Feb. 4, 1977); "In Pursuit of Clarity," review by Christina Robb in The Boston Globe (Dec. 24, 1976); review in Worldview (Jan/Feb 1977); review by George H. Straley in The Lutheran (Jan. 19, 1977); review in The Hamden Chronicle (Nov. 18, 1976); "Sensitive Analysis," review by Ann Martin in The Living Church (Jan. 9, 1977); "C.S. Lewis and Everyday Issues," review in Christianity Today (Jan. 21, 1977); review in The Covenant Companion (Jan. 15, 1977); review by Roger Hazelton in Andover Newton Quarterly, 18.3 (Jan. 1978), 1976-1978 (Box 3, Folder 35)
      - re. C.S. Lewis: The Shape of His Faith and Thought - Review in Reflection, 18.3 (summer 1979) by Andrew J. Burgess; review in The Princeton Seminary Bulletin (Box 3, Folder 36)
      - re. The Grammar of Faith (San Francisco: Harper and Row, 1978.) - Preface; reviews in The New Catholic World and Commonweal; review by Robert L. Perkins (Box 3, Folder 37)
      - re. The Grammar of Faith - review by Andrew J. Burgess in Reflection, 77.2 (Jan. 1980) (Box 3, Folder 38)
      - re. Making Christian Sense (Spirituality and the Christian Life series, ed. Richard H. Bell. Philadelphia: The Westminster Press, 1984): Typescripts: Ch. I [untitled]; Ch. II - "Making Sense Emotionally"; Ch. III - "Making Sense Morally"; Ch. IV - "Making Sense With the Will"; Ch. V - "Making Sense With One's Thought" (typescripts) (Box 3, Folder 39)
      - re. Making Christian Sense - reviews by Vincent A. McCarthy (1-6), Howard Conn, 1984, 1985 (Box 3, Folder 40)
    - Other book-length manuscripts
      - Consciousness: Ch. I - "About Being Conscious" (Box 3, Folder 41)
      - Consciousness: Ch. II - "Science, Learning, and Our Consciousness" (Box 3, Folder 42)
      - Consciousness: Table of Contents; Notes to Mrs. Orr [editor?]; Ch. IV - "Consciousness in the Religious Stage of Life"; Ch. X - "The Historicity and Temporality of Consciousness" (Box 3, Folder 43)
      - Consciousness: Ch. V - "The Alienation of Consciousness" (Box 3, Folder 44)
      - Kierkegaard, Soren: Ch. I - "An Introduction to the Problem" (Box 4, Folder 45)
      - Kierkegaard, Soren: Ch. I - "An Introduction to the Problem"; Various excerpts from other chapters (Box 4, Folder 46)
      - Kierkegaard, Soren: Ch. I - "The Problem"; notes on "Theology and Falsification"; "Articles, Reviews, published 1953-54"; "Terms of Award - United States Educational Exchange Grant";Ch. I - "An Introduction"; Ch. II - "The Nature of the Authorship"; Misc. notes; Letter from U of MN Press rejecting a manuscript, 6/24/57 (Box 4, Folder 47)
      - Kierkegaard, Soren: Ch. II - "The Authorship Considered" (Box 4, Folder 48)
      - Kierkegaard, Soren: Ch. II - "A Glance at a Contemporary Effort in Danish Literature" (Box 4, Folder 49)
      - Kierkegaard, Soren; Ch. III - "The Literature as an Argument" (Box 4, Folder 50)
      - Kierkegaard, Soren: Ch. III - "A New Way of Philosophizing" (Box 4, Folder 51)
      - Kierkegaard, Soren: Ch. IV - "The Bible and Certainty"; Ch. V - "History and the Sciences"; Ch. VI - "Truth Is Subjectivity: Some Radical Criticisms"; Ch. VII - "Truth as Subjectivity: Some Logical Considerations"; Ch. VIII - "Some Epistemological Questions"; Ch. IX - "Kierkegaard and Metaphysics" (Box 4, Folder 52)
      - Kierkegaard, Soren: Ch. IV - "Cognitive Truth and Scripture" (Box 4, Folder 53)
      - Kierkegaard, Soren: Ch. IV - "Knowledge and Scripture" (Box 4, Folder 54)
      - Kierkegaard, Soren: Ch. V - "History and the Sciences" (Box 4, Folder 55)
      - Kierkegaard, Soren: Ch. VI - "Truth Is Subjectivity: Some Radical Criticisms" (3 different versions) (Box 4, Folder 56)
      - Kierkegaard, Soren: Ch. VII - "Truth as Subjectivity: Positive Considerations"; Ch. IX - "Kierkegaard and the Nature of Philosophy" (Box 4, Folder 57)
      - Kierkegaard, Soren: Ch. VII - "Truth as Subjectivity: Positive Considerations"; Ch. VIII - "Kierkegaard and Metaphysics" (Box 4, Folder 58)
      - Kierkegaard, Soren: Ch. VII - "Truth as Subjectivity: Some Logical Considerations" (Box 4, Folder 59)
      - Kierkegaard, Soren; Ch. VIII - "Some Epistemological Questions" (Box 5, Folder 60)
      - Kierkegaard, Soren; Ch. VIII - "Some Epistemological Questions"; "Kierkegaard and Metaphysics" (Box 5, Folder 61)
      - Kierkegaard, Soren; Ch. IX - "Kierkegaard and Metaphysics" (Box 5, Folder 62)
      - Kierkegaard, Soren; Ch. IX - "Kierkegaard and the Nature of Philosophy" (Box 5, Folder 63)
      - Kierkegaard, Soren; Ch. X - "Indirect Communication" (Box 5, Folder 64)
      - Kierkegaard, Soren; Ch. X - "Indirect Communication"; Misc. excerpts (Box 5, Folder 65)
      - Kierkegaard, Soren: "Preface" (Box 5, Folder 66)
      - Kierkegaard, Soren: "Preface"; Table of Contents; Ch. I - "An Introduction to the Problem"; Ch. II - "The Authorship Considered"; Ch. III - "The Literature as an Argument"; Ch. X - "Indirect Communication"; Ch. XI - "Kierkegaard and the Sermon" (Box 5, Folder 67)
      - Kierkegaard, Soren: Table of Contents; Letter to Richard regarding the chapter on S. K.; Ch. XIII - Soren Kierkegaard; "Contemporaneity with Christ" (Box 5, Folder 68)
      - Kierkegaard, Soren: Table of Contents; Preface; "Kierkegaard and Logic"; "Some Reflections About the Humanities"; Ch. IV; Ch. V - "History and the Sciences"; Ch. VI - "Truth is Subjectivity: Some Negative Considerations" (Box 5, Folder 69)
      - Kierkegaard, Soren: Untitled; Ch. IV - "Christian Scripture and Knowledge" (Box 5, Folder 70)
      - Kierkegaard, Soren: Untitled chapter about S. K.'s "The Subjective Truth, Inwardness ... "; Ch. II - "A Glance at a Contemporary Effort in Danish Literature"; Ch. III - "A New Way of Philosophizing"; Ch. V - "History and the Sciences"; Ch. VII - "Truth as Subjectivity: Some Logical Considerations" (Box 5, Folder 71)
      - Ch. II - "Psychoanalysis and Religion" (Box 6, Folder 72)
  - Forewords/Introductions to Books
    - Introduction to Edifying Discourses by Soren Kierkegaard, New York: Harper, 1958, Torchbooks edition (Box 6, Folder 73)
    - re. Introduction to Edifying Discourses, 1958 (Box 6, Folder 74)
    - Foreword to Kierkegaard and Consciousness by Adi Shmueli. xi-xv. Princeton, NJ: Princeton University Press, 1971. (Box 6, Folder 75)
    - Foreword to The New Obedience: Kierkegaard on Imitating Christ by Bradley R. Dewey. vii-xii. Washington, D.C. and Cleveland: Corpus Books, 1968. (Box 6, Folder 76)
  - Chapters in Books
    - "Philosophical Criticism and American Theology." In Report on the Relation Between Philosophy and Theology, Bossey, Switzerland: The Ecumenical Institute. (2 typescripts, 1 manuscript), 1953 (Box 6, Folder 77)
    - "Soren A. Kierkegaard." In Christian Ethics: Sources of the Living Tradition, ed. Waldo Beach and H. Richard Niebuhr. 414-43. New York: Ronald Press, 1955 (Box 6, Folder 78)
    - "Soren Kierkegaard: Faith in a Tragic World." In The Tragic Vision and the Christian Faith ed. by Nathan Scott, NY: Associated Press, 1957 (Box 6, Folder 79)
    - "Can We Educate Ministers Scientifically?" In The Making of Ministers: Essays on Clergy Training Today, ed. Keith R. Bridston and Dwight W. Culver. 2-28. Minneapolis: Augsburg, 1964 (typescript draft) (Box 6, Folder 80)
    - "About Our Capacity to Talk." In Communication, 215-229. Northern Illinois University Press, 1968 (?) (2 typescripts, 2 copies of typescripts, 1 manuscript) (Box 6, Folder 81)
    - "Kierkegaard and Philosophy." In New Themes in Christian Philosophy, ed. Ralph M. McInerny. 13-33. Notre Dame and London: University of Notre Dame Press (3 typescripts, 3 typescript copies, 1 manuscript), 1968 (Box 6, Folder 82)
    - "Theology and Belief." In Essays on Kierkegaard, ed. Jerry H. Gill. 186-197. Minneapolis: Burgess, 1969 (1 typescript, 2 typescripts) Also in Theology Today 22, no. 3, (October 1965): 358-371. (1 journal offprint) (Box 6, Folder 83)
    - "Wittgenstein and Theology" in New Essays on Religious Language ed. by Dallas M. High. New York: Oxford University Press, 1969 (Box 6, Folder 83)
    - "Kierkegaard and Logic." In Kierkegaard's Presence in Contemporary American Life, ed. Lewis A. Lawson. 60-77. Metuchen, NJ: Scarecrow Press, 1970 (2 typescript copies) (Box 6, Folder 84)
    - "Nygren and Linguistic Analysis: Language and Meaning." In The Philosophy and Theology of Anders Nygren, ed. Charles Kegley. 70-91. Carbondale, IL: Southern Illinois University Press, 1970 (2 typescripts, 4 typescript copies, 1 manuscript, letter from Charles W. Kegley) (Box 6, Folder 85)
    - "Theological Education and Personal Faith." In The Continuing Quest, ed. James Hofrenning. 43-67. Minneapolis, MN: Augsburg Publishing House, 1970. (1 manuscript, 3 typescripts, correspondence) (Box 7, Folder 86)
    - "Contemporary Evangelical Faith: An Assessment and Critique" in Evangelicals: what they believe, who they are, where they are changing / edited by David F. Wells and John D. Woodbridge. Nashville: Abingdon Press, 1975 (Box 7, Folder 87)
    - "Wittgenstein and the Self." In Essays on Kierkegaard and Wittgenstein: On Understanding the Self, ed. Richard H. Bell and Ronald E. Hustwit. 10-31. Wooster, Ohio: The College of Wooster, 1978 (Box 7, Folder 87)
    - "About Communication: Ethico-Religious Considerations." In Communication and Spirituality, ed. Clifford G. Christians. New York: Science Publishing Inc., 1979 (1 computer printout, 3 copies of typescript, 1 manuscript) (Box 7, Folder 88)
    - "About Black Theology" in Black Theology: a Documentary History, 1966-1979, ed. Gayraud S. Wilmore and James H. Cone. Maryknoll, N.Y.: Orbis Books, 1979 (Box 7, Folder 89)
    - "About Being a Person: Kierkegaard's Fear and Trembling." In Kierkegaard's Fear and Trembling: Critical Appraisals, ed. Robert L. Perkins. 81-99. University, AL: The University of Alabama Press, 1981 (3 typescript copies, 2 manuscripts) (Box 7, Folder 89)
    - "Post-Kierkegaard: Remarks about Being a Person." In Kierkegaard's Truth: The Disclosure of the Self, ed. Joseph H. Smith M.D. 3-22. New Haven and London: Yale University Press, 1981 (3 typescript copies) (Box 7, Folder 90)
    - "The Grammar of Faith." In The Grammar of the Heart: New Essays in Moral Philosophy and Theology, ed. Richard H. Bell. 3-20. San Francisco: Harper and Row, 1988. Reprint of "What Theology Is and Does Again," from The Grammar of Faith. (1 typescript) (Box 7, Folder 90)
    - "Making Sense Morally" In The Grammar of the Heart: New Essays in Moral Philosophy and Theology, ed. Richard H. Bell. 3-20. San Francisco: Harper and Row, 1988 (Box 7, Folder 91)
    - "Learning to Theologize." In Wittgenstein: Attention to Particulars: Essays in Honour of Rush Rhees (1905-89), ed. D.Z. Phillips and Peter Winch. 194-200. New York: St. Martin's Press, 1989 (1 typescript, 3 copies of typescripts, 2 computer printouts) (Box 7, Folder 92)
    - "Theology, Atheism, and Theism." In Contemporary Perspectives on Religious Epistemology, ed. R. Douglas Geivett and Brendan Sweetman. 104-115. New York: Oxford University Press, 1992. Reprinted from Paul Holmer, The Grammar of Faith, 1978 (1 manuscript) (Box 7, Folder 93)
  - Published Articles / Lectures
    - "Christianity and the Arts." Covenant Quarterly 3, no. 2: 3-10 (copy of journal), 1943 May (Box 7, Folder 94)
    - "Continuity and Discontinuity in Thought About God." Augustana Quarterly 24, no. 3: 195-208 (copy of journal), 1945 Jul (Box 7, Folder 95)
    - "Kierkegaard, A Religious Author." American-Scandinavian Review 33, no. 2: 147-52 (typescript and 2 journals), 1945 Jun (Box 7, Folder 96)
    - "Soren A. Kierkegaard." The Augustana Quarterly 27, no. 3: 271-5 (1 copy of journal), 1948 Jul (Box 7, Folder 97)
    - "The Literature of Devotion." Covenant Quarterly 10, no. 3: 77-84. (1 manuscript, notes), 1950 Aug (Box 7, Folder 98)
    - "Christ and the Teacher." Journal of the Association of Lutheran College Faculties 3: 13-24 (typescript with manuscript revisions; miscellaneous sheets of revised typescript; 2 copies of final draft), 1951 Jan (Box 7, Folder 99)
    - "Spirit in the Thought of Nicholas Berdyaev." Lutheran Quarterly 3, no. 1: 3-22. (1 manuscript, notes: "Sex: The Masculine and the Feminine," "The Conscious and the Unconscious," "Berdyaev and Knowledge," "Biographical," Metaphy. Principles," "God - Man - Freedom," "Positive," "Negative," "Berdyaev Bibliography," "Footnotes," excerpts of a typescript.), 1951 Feb (Box 8, Folder 100)
    - "Soren Kierkegaard and the University of Minnesota." Meddelelser fra Soren Kierkegaard Selskabet (Reports from the Soren Kierkegaard Society. Quarterly Review) 3, no. 1: 73-76 (typescript and 2 journals), 1951 Mar (Box 8, Folder 101)
    - "'To Be Christ' Unto All Men." Campus Lutheran (Lutheran Student Association, Chicago) 3, no. 3: 4-9 (typescript and 2 journals), 1952 Jan (Box 8, Folder 102)
    - "Evangelism and Our Culture." Covenant Quarterly 12, no. 1: 3-12 (typescript and copy of journal), 1952 Feb (Box 8, Folder 103)
    - "The Nature of Theology." Journal of Religious Thought 9, no. 2 (Spring-Summer 1952): 137-15 (3 typescripts, 2 journal extracts, 2 complete journals) (Box 8, Folder 104)
    - "Religion and Illusion" (Summer Convocation Address). Chicago Lutheran Seminary Record 57: 26-32 (4 typescripts, 1 loose page, 1 journal extract, 1 complete copy of journal), 1952 Oct (Box 8, Folder 105)
    - "Kierkegaard and Ethical Theory." Ethics: An International Journal of Social, Political, and Legal Philosophy 63, no. 3, pt. 1: 157-70 (1 manuscript, 1 typescript, 1 style sheets supplied by the journal, 1 journal extract), 1953 Apr (Box 8, Folder 106)
    - "Kierkegaard and Kinds of Discourse." Meddelelser fra Soren Kierkegaard Selskabet (Reports from the Soren Kierkegaard Society. Quarterly Review) 4, no. 4: 1-5 (1 manuscript, 2 typescripts, 1 set of galleys, 2 journal extracts), 1953 Dec (Box 8, Folder 107)
    - "Law and Gospel Re-examined." Theology Today 10, no. 4: 474-81. (2 journal extracts; 1 typescript; 1 German translation, "Gesetz und Evangelium aufs neue untersucht", 1958), 1954 Jan (Box 8, Folder 108)